Beecher, James Chaplin, 1828-1886. Papers, 1850-1946: A Finding Aid
Papers, 1850-1946
A-123
Schlesinger Library, Radcliffe Institute
JAMES C. BEECHER, 1828-1886
1 + 1/2 file boxes, 1 folio+ folder
Correspondence, diaries, photographs of James C. Beecher, son of Lyman Beecher, and other family members.
Accession numbers: 428,446,482
Gift of Mr. and Mrs. Alfred T. Abeles, Wilmette, Ill. Received April, June and October 1962.
BIOGRAPHY
This is a collection of material pertaining to the family of James C. Beecher (1828-1886) and his wife Frances Johnson Beecher Perkins. He was the son of Lyman Beecher, a picture of whose portrait is included. The family letters reveal personalities, background and interests of those who lived in the Civil War period. James joined the United States Army becoming a Colonel of the First North Carolina Colored Volunteers which fought at Fort Sumpter and in Florida. He praised the courage and ability of his negro troops. His correspondence with his military commanders reveals his impatience and lack of confidence in the operation of the Freedmen's Bureau, the treatment of the Refugee Freedmen and the policy of distribution of land of abandoned plantations. Two letters to Charles Sumner review the problems of Reconstruction. [Written by Elizabeth Bancroft Schlesinger]
SCOPE AND CONTENT
Correspondence, diaries, and photos comprise the collection. Included are James Beecher's correspondence about the Civil War, Reconstruction, and the Freedmen's Bureau, and papers of his wife, Frances (Johnson) Beecher Perkins, their adopted twin daughters, Mary Frances (Beecher) Beecher and Margaret (Beecher) Ward, and other Beechers and Johnsons.
There is related material at the Schlesinger Library; see Beecher-Stowe family papers, 1798-1956 (A-102) and (A-102.1). For photographs of James C. Beecher and family, see A-102, folder 435.
Additional catalog entries:
U.S.-History-Civil War; Negroes; Chicago, World's Fair, 1893; Mount Holyoke Seminary; Diaries; Dickinson, Anna Elizabeth, 1842-1932; Gillette, William, 1855-1937; Stowe, Harriet Beecher, 1811-1896; Hooker, Isabella Beecher, 1822-1907; Beecher, Catharine, 1800-1878; Beecher, Thomas K., 1824-1900; Warner, Charles Dudley, 1829-1900; Marcy, Henry Orlando, 1837-1924; Perkins, Frances Johnson Beecher, 1832-; Beecher, Mary Frances Beecher, -1952; Ward, Margaret Beecher
CONTAINER LIST
Box 1: Folders 1-58
Box 2: Folders 59-78
INVENTORY
- Genealogical information relating to the James C. Beecher family, 1.
- Photograph of 1838 Marchand portrait of Lyman Beecher, 2.
- 2 photographs of Frances (Johnson) Beecher Perkins, 3.
- Perkins, Frances (Johnson) Beecher, Two Years with a Colored Regiment. A Woman's Experience. Article from New England Magazine, Jan. 1898., 4.
- Flyer: The Beecher Family School for Young Girls, Cos Cob, Conn. Operated by Frances (Johnson) Beecher Perkins, 5.
- Johnson, Frances. Notebook kept at Mt. Holyoke Seminary. 1850-1855., 6.
- Johnson, Frances. 3 letters to sister, Eliza (Johnson) Butler. 1851-1858., 7.
- Johnson, Frances. 1 letter to "cousin". 1855., 8.
- Beecher, James C. 6 letters to Frances Johnson. 1863., 9.
- Dickinson, Anna E. 1 letter to James C. Beecher. 1863., 10.
- Stowe, Harriet Beecher. 1 letter to James C. Beecher. 1863., 11.
- Beecher, James C. Correspondence. 1863-1864. 1 letter from C.D. Warner., 12.
- JCB. 1 letter to Frances' mother, Olive S. Johnson. 1864., 13.
- JCB. 8 letters to Frances Johnson. Mar.-June, 1864., 14.
- Johnson, Frances. 6 letters to JCB. May-June, 1864., 15.
- JCB. 12 letters to wife, Frances (Johnson) Beecher. July-Dec., 1864., 16.
- Beecher, Frances (Johnson). 3 letters to husband, JCB. 1864., 17.
- Beecher, Henry Ward. 1 letter from Z. Platt re: JCB. 1864., 18.
- JCB. 2 letters to wife, Frances (Johnson) Beecher. 1865., 19.
- JCB. Correspondence with Gen. R. Saxton. 1865., 20.
- JCB. 2 letters to Charles Sumner. 1865., 21.
- Item removed from folder 21, F+D.1.
- JCB. Correspondence, etc. 1865., 22.
- Beecher, Frances (Johnson). Citation from Union League "for exertions in behalf of the colored people." 1865., 23.
- Copy of act to establish a Bureau for the relief of Freedmen and Refugees, Mar. 3, 1865., 24.
- Circular No. 2, Bureau of Refugees, Freedmen, and Abandoned Lands, May 19, 1865., 25.
- JCB. Correspondence. 1866. 2 letters from H.O. Marcy., 26.
- JCB. Commission of Brigadier General letters of endorsement. 1866., 27.
- Johnson, Samuel W. 5 letters to sister, Frances (Johnson) Beecher. 1866-1869., 28.
- JCB. 2 letters rec. 1867., 29.
- Beecher, Catharine. 1 letter to JCB, Frances (Johnson) Beecher, and Julia Beecher. 1867., 30.
- Beecher, Thomas K. 1 letter to JCB. 1867., 31.
- Beecher, Isabella. 1 letter to JCB. 1867., 32.
- Beecher, Frances (Johnson). 1 letter from "PBT." 1867., 33.
- Beecher, Charles. 1 letter to JCB. 1868., 34.
- Johnson, Samuel C. 3 letters to daughter, Frances. 1869-1871., 35.
- Perkins, Mary Foote (Beecher). 1 letter to JCB and Frances. circa 1875?., 36.
- JCB. 1 letter to mother-in-law, Olive S. Johnson. 1875?., 37.
- Beecher, Frances (Johnson). 3 letters to mother, Olive S. Johnson. 1877., 38.
- JCB. 1 letter to?. circa 1880?., 39.
- Beecher, Margaret. 1 letter to grandmother. 1883., 40.
- Johnson, Olive S. 19 letters to daughter, Frances. 1884-1891., 41.
- Johnson, Olive S. 12 letters to daughter, Frances. Undated., 42.
- Beecher, Frances (Johnson). 2 letters to JCB. 1885., 43.
- Beecher, S.S. 1 letter to Frances (Johnson) Beecher. 1886., 44.
- Beecher, Mary Frances. 1 letter to mother, Frances (Johnson) Beecher. 1887., 45.
- Beecher, Frances (Johnson). 1 letter rec. 1887., 46.
- Beecher, Frances (Johnson). 9 letters to mother. 1888-1889., 47.
- FJB. 8 letters to mother. Undated., 48.
- FJB Kathie Beecher. 1 letter to Margaret Beecher. 1889., 49.
- Beecher, Isabella Jones Porter. 1 letter to FJB. 1889., 50.
- Johnson, Adalene E. 1 letter to mother, Olive S. Johnson. 1889., 51.
- Gillette, William. 23 letters to May (Mary Frances) Beecher. 1889-1898., 52.
- Correspondence between May and Margaret Beecher and their mother, Frances (Johnson) Beecher, re: Chicago World's Fair. 1893., 53.
- Perkins, Frances (Johnson) Beecher. 10 letters rec. 1893-1901., 54.
- Beecher, Thomas K. 1 letter to Frances (Johnson) Beecher Perkins. 1895., 55.
- Beecher, May. 1 letter to William Gillette. 1895., 56.
- Perkins, Frances (Johnson) Beecher. Draft to William Gillette. 1895., 57.
- Gillette, William. 1 letter to FJBP. 1896?., 58.
- Beecher, May. 2 letters rec. 1897., 59.
- Beecher, May. 3 letters to Henry Ward Beecher, II. 1898., 60.
- Hooker, Isabella (Beecher). 1 letter to niece, May Beecher. 1898., 61.
- "LBB". 1 letter to "cousin." 1900., 62.
- Beecher, May (Beecher). 2 letters to mother, FJBP. 1900, 1903., 63.
- Beecher, May (Beecher). 14 letters to mother. Undated., 64.
- Beecher, Katherine. 1 letter to mother, FJBP. 1902., 65.
- FJBP. Religious diary. 1902-1903., 66.
- FJBP. Letters to daughters, May, Margaret, and Katherine. 1902-1903., 67.
- FJBP. Letters to daughters. Undated., 68.
- Hooker, Isabella (Beecher). 1 letter to May (Beecher) Beecher. 1902., 69.
- Ward, Margaret (Beecher). 2 letters to sister, May (Beecher) Beecher. 1903., 70.
- Beecher, Julia. 2 letters to May (Beecher) Beecher. 1903-1904., 71.
- Brown, Kate Pingor. 1 letter to Mrs. Beecher. 1919., 72.
- Beecher, May (Beecher). 2 letters from John Wanamaker. 1920., 73.
- Abeles, Alfred Beecher. Letters to family. 1943., 74.
- Abeles, Margaret. 1 letter to mother. 1943., 75.
- Beecher, Henry Ward, III. Letters. 1943., 76.
- Abeles, Shirley. 1 letter to May (Beecher) Beecher. 1946., 77.
- Undated, incomplete mss., 78.